<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">WWaW_Atwood-Intro</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl><publisher>TRP document creator: dkj004@bucknell.edu</publisher></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<pb n="1"/>
				<pb n="2"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_1" n="N001"/>Introduction
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_2" n="N002"/>This new volume of the Paris Review’s highly praised and
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_3" n="N003"/>praiseworthy series of interviews with writers is a departure
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_4" n="N004"/>from the norm. Previous collections have mixed the genders; this
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_5" n="N005"/>one is unisexual. That the editors have chosen to bring together,
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_6" n="N006"/>within the same covers, fifteen writers as diverse as Dorothy Parker
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_7" n="N007"/>and Nadine Gordimer, <persName key="Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972." ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/61562401" ana="webannotation:http://temp.lincsproject.ca/5YwP0OGEDJ1">Marianne Moore</persName> and Rebecca West, Isak
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_8" n="N008"/>Dinesen and Lillian Hellman, Mary McCarthy and Katherine
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_9" n="N009"/>Anne Porter, over what, in some cases, would doubtless be their
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_10" n="N010"/>dead bodies, merely because they share a double-X chronosome,
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_11" n="N011"/>is not due to a sudden mental aberration. Rather it has been the
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_12" n="N012"/>result of readers' requests. Why not a gathering of women writers?
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_13" n="N013"/>the editor were asked. Well, why not? Which is not quite the
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_14" n="N014"/>same thing as why.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_15" n="N001"/>To some the answer would seem self-evident: women writers
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_16" n="N002"/>belong together because they are different from men, and the
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_17" n="N003"/>writing they do is different as well and cannot be read with the
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_18" n="N004"/>same eyeglasses as those used for the reading of male writers. Nor
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_19" n="N005"/>can writing by women be read in the same way by men as it can
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_20" n="N006"/>by women, and vice versa. For many women, Heathcliff is a
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_21" n="N007"/>romantic hero; for many men, he is a posturing oaf they'd like
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_22" n="N008"/>to punch in the nose. For many men, The Ginger Man's Sebastian
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_23" n="N009"/>Dangerfield is an energy-packed rebel; for many women, he is
					<lb facs="#facs_2_l_24" n="N010"/>an immature and tiresome wife-beater. Paradise Lost reads dif-
				</p>
				<pb n="3"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l" n="N001"/>ferently when viewed by the daughters of Eve, and with <persName key="Milton, John, 1608-1674." ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17226855" ana="webannotation:http://temp.lincsproject.ca/80kfuzKFLrX">Milton</persName>'s
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_1" n="N002"/>browbeaten secretarial daughters in mind; and so on down
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_2" n="N003"/>through the canon.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_12" n="N001"/>Such gender-polarized analyses can reach beyond subject-
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_15" n="N002"/>matter and point of view to encompass matters of structure and
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_16" n="N003"/>style: are women really more subjective? do their novels really
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_45" n="N004"/>end with questions? Especially in this age of semiotics, gender-
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_46" n="N005"/>linked analysis may seek to explore attitudes towards language
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_47" n="N006"/>itself. Is there a distinct female écriture? Does the mother-tongue
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_48" n="N007"/>really belong to mothers, or is it yet one more male-shaped in-
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_49" n="N008"/>stitution bent, like foot-binding, on the deformation and hobbling
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_50" n="N009"/>of women? I have had it suggested to me, in all seriousness, that
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_51" n="N010"/>women ought not to write at all, since to do so is to dip one's
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_52" n="N011"/>hand, like Shakespeares dyer, into a medium both sullied and
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_53" n="N012"/>sullying. (This suggestion was not made telepathically, but in
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_54" n="N013"/>spoken sentences; since, for polemicists as for writers themselves,
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_55" n="N014"/>the alternative to language is silence.)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_8" n="N001"/>I was recently on a panel—that polygonal form of discourse so
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_9" n="N002"/>beloved of the democratic twentieth century—consisting entirely
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_10" n="N003"/>of women, including Jan Morris, who used to be James Morris,
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_11" n="N004"/>and Nayantara Sahgal of India. From the audience came the
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_13" n="N005"/>question, "How do you feel about being on a panel of women?"
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_14" n="N006"/>We all prevaricated. Some of us protested that we had been on
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_17" n="N007"/>lots of panels that included men; others said that most panels
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_18" n="N008"/>were male, with a woman dotted here and there for decorative
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_19" n="N009"/>effect, like parsley. Jan Morris said that she was in the process of
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_20" n="N010"/>transcending gender and was aiming at becoming a horse, to
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_21" n="N011"/>which Nayantara Sahgal replied that she hoped it was an English
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_22" n="N012"/>horse, since in some other, poorer countries, horses were not
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_23" n="N013"/>treated very well. Which underlined, for all of us, that there are
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_24" n="N014"/>categories other than male and female worth considering.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_25" n="N001"/>I suppose we all should have said. "Why not?" Still, I was
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_26" n="N002"/>intrigued by our collective uneasiness. No woman writer wants
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_27" n="N003"/>to be overlooked and undervalued for being a woman, but few,
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_28" n="N004"/>it seems, wish to be defined solely by gender, or constrained by
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_29" n="N005"/>loyalties to it alone—an attitude which may puzzle, hurt or enrage
					<lb facs="#facs_3_l_30" n="N006"/>those whose political priorities cause them to view writing as a
				</p>
				<pb n="4"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l" n="N001"/>tool, a means towards an end, rather than as a Muse who will
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_1" n="N002"/>desert you if you break trust. In the interview which begins this
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_2" n="N003"/>collection. Dorothy Parker articles the dilemma:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_36" n="N001"/>I'm a feminist, and God knows I'm loyal to my sex, and
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_37" n="N002"/>you must remember that from my very early days, when
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_38" n="N003"/>this city was scarcely safe from buffaloes, I was in the struggle
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_39" n="N004"/>for equal rights for women. But when we paraded through
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_40" n="N005"/>the catcalls of men and when we chained ourselves to lamp
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_41" n="N006"/>posts to try to get out equality—dear child, we didn't foresee
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_42" n="N007"/>those female writers. (Pp. 114-115)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_3" n="N001"/>Male writers may suffer grains on their single-minded dedi-
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_4" n="N002"/>cation to their art for reasons of class or race or nationality, but
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_5" n="N003"/>so far no male writer is likely to be asked to sit on a panel addressing
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_6" n="N004"/>itself to the special problems of the male writer, or be expected
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_7" n="N005"/>to support another writer simply because he happens to be a man.
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_8" n="N006"/>Such things are asked of women writers all the time, and it makes
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_9" n="N007"/>them jumpy.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_12" n="N001"/>Virginia Woolf may have been right about the androgynous
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_13" n="N002"/>nature of the artist, but she was right also about the differences
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_14" n="N003"/>in social situation these androgynous artists are certain to en-
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_15" n="N004"/>counter. We may agree with Nadine Gordimer when she says,
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_30" n="N005"/>"By and large, I don't think it matters a damn what sex a writer
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_31" n="N006"/>is, so long as the work is that of a real writer" (p. 260), if what
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_32" n="N007"/>she means is that it shouldn't matter, in any true assesment of
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_33" n="N008"/>talent of accomplishment, but unfortunately it often has mattered,
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_34" n="N009"/>to other people. When Joyce Carol Oates is asked the "woman"
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_35" n="N010"/>question. phrased in her case as "What are the advantages of being
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_43" n="N011"/>a woman writer?", she makes a virtue of necessity:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_44" n="N001"/>Advantages! Too many to enumerate, probably. Since,
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_45" n="N002"/>being a woman. I can't be taken altogether seriously by the
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_46" n="N003"/>sort of male critics who rank writers 1, 2. 3 in the public
					<lb facs="#facs_4_l_10" n="N004"/>press. I am free, I suppose, to do as I like. (P. 382)
				</p>
				<pb n="5"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l" n="N001"/>Joan Didion is asked the same question in its negative form—
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_1" n="N002"/>"disadvantages" instead of "advantages"—and also focuses on so-
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_2" n="N003"/>cial differences, social acceptance and role:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_36" n="N001"/>When I was starting to write—in the late fifties, early
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_37" n="N002"/>sixties—there was a kind of social tradition in which male
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_38" n="N003"/>novelists could operate. Hard drinkers, bad livers. Wives,
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_39" n="N004"/>wars, big fish, Africa, Paris, no second acts. A man who
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_40" n="N005"/>wrote novels had a role in the world, and he could play
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_41" n="N006"/>that role and do whatever he wanted behind it. A woman
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_42" n="N007"/>who wrote novels had no particular role. Women who wrote
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_43" n="N008"/>novels were quite often perceived as invalids. Carson
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_44" n="N009"/>McCullers, Jane Bowles. Flannery O'Connor of course.
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_45" n="N010"/>Novels by women tended to be described, even by their
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_46" n="N011"/>publishers, as sensitive. I'm not sure this is so true anymore,
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_47" n="N012"/>but it certainly was at the time, and I didn't much like it.
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_48" n="N013"/>I dealt with it the same way I deal with everything. I just
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_49" n="N014"/>tended my own garden, didn't pay much attention, be-
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_50" n="N015"/>haved—I suppose—deviously. (Pp. 324-325)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_3" n="N001"/>I think of Marianne Moore, living decorously with her mother
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_4" n="N002"/>and her "dark" furniture, her height of social rebellion the cou-
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_5" n="N003"/>rageous ignoring of the need for chaperones at Village literary
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_6" n="N004"/>parties, and wonder how many male writers could have lived such
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_7" n="N005"/>a circumscribed life and survived the image.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_8" n="N001"/>Not least among perceived social differences is the difficulty
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_9" n="N002"/>woman writers have experienced in being taken "altogether
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_10" n="N003"/>seriously" as legitimate artists. Ezra Pound, writing in the second
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_11" n="N004"/>decade of this century, spoke for many male authors and critics
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_21" n="N005"/>before and since: "I distrust the 'female artist.' . . . Not wildly
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_14" n="N006"/>anti-feminist we are yet to be convinced that any woman ever
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_15" n="N007"/>invented anything in the arts." (Carpenter, A Serious Character,
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_16" n="N008"/>Houghton Mifflin, 1988, p. 239.) Cognate with this view of
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_17" n="N009"/>writing as a male preserve has been the image of women writers
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_18" n="N010"/>as lightweight puffballs, neurotic freaks suffering from what Edna
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_19" n="N011"/>O'Brien calls "a double dose of masochism: the masochisim of
					<lb facs="#facs_5_l_20" n="N012"/>the woman and that of the artist" (p. 342), or, if approved of, as
				</p>
				<pb n="6"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l" n="N001"/>honorary men. Femininity and excellence, it seemed, were mu-
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_1" n="N002"/>tually exclusive. Thus Katherine Anne Porter:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_34" n="N001"/>If there is such a thing as a man's mind and a woman's
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_35" n="N002"/>mind—and I'm sure there is—it isn't what most critics mean
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_36" n="N003"/>when they talk about the two. If I show wisdom, they say
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_37" n="N004"/>I have a masculine mind. If I am silly and irrelevant—and
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_38" n="N005"/>Edmund Wilson says I often am—why then they say I have
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_39" n="N006"/>a typically feminine mind!... But I haven't ever found it
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_40" n="N007"/>unnatural to be a woman. (P. 65)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_2" n="N001"/>The interviewer responds with a question that is asked, in one
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_3" n="N002"/>form or another, not only of almost every woman included in
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_4" n="N003"/>this book, but of almost every woman writer ever interviewed:
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_5" n="N004"/>"But haven't you found that being a woman presented to you, as
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_6" n="N005"/>an artist, certain special problems?"
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_27" n="N001"/>Katherine Anne Porter’s reply—“I think that’S very true and
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_28" n="N002"/>very right"—is by no means the only one possible. Some, such
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_29" n="N003"/>as Mary McCarthy, are clearly impatient with the question itself.
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_30" n="N004"/>McCarthy accepts some version of the "masculine" versus the
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_31" n="N005"/>"feminine" sensibility, but assigns herself firmly with the former.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_7" n="N001"/>INTERVIEWER: What do you think of women writers, or
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_8" n="N002"/>do you think the category "woman writer" should not be
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_9" n="N003"/>made?
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_22" n="N001"/>MCCARTHY: Some women writers make it. I mean, there's
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_23" n="N002"/>a certain kind of woman writer who's a capital W, capital
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_24" n="N003"/>W. Virginia Woolf certainly was one, and Katherine Mans-
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_25" n="N004"/>field was one, and Elizabeth Bowen is one. Katherine Anne
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_26" n="N005"/>Porter? Don't think she really is—I mean, her writing is
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_32" n="N006"/>certainly very feminine, but I would say that there wasn't
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_33" n="N007"/>this “WW” business in Katherine Anne Porter. Who else?
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_41" n="N008"/>There's Eudora Welty, who's certainly not a "Woman
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_42" n="N009"/>Winter," though she's become one lately.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_10" n="N001"/>INTERVIEWER: What is it that happens to make this
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_11" n="N002"/>change?
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_6_l_12" n="N001"/>MCCARTHY: I think they become interested in décor. You
				</p>
				<pb n="7"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l" n="N001"/>notice the change in Elizabeth Bowen. Her early work is
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_1" n="N002"/>much more masculine. Her later work has much more
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_2" n="N003"/>drapery in it . . . I was going to write a piece at some point
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_3" n="N004"/>about this called "Sense and Sensibility," dividing women
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_4" n="N005"/>writers into these two. I am for the ones who represent
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_5" n="N006"/>sense ... (Pp. 189-190)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_35" n="N001"/>Cynthia Ozick goes much farther; she refuses such dichotomies
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_36" n="N002"/>altogether:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_7" n="N001"/>INTERVIEWER: you have written about the writer as
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_8" n="N002"/>being genderless and living in the world of "as if" rather
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_9" n="N003"/>than being restrained by her . . .
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_6" n="N001"/>OZICK: Parochial temporary commitments. . . . A writer
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_33" n="N002"/>is someone born with a gift. An athlete can run. A painter
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_34" n="N003"/>can paint. A writer has a facility with words. A good writer
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_37" n="N004"/>can also think. Isn't that enough to define a writer by?
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_38" n="N005"/>(P. 304)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_10" n="N001"/>Cynthia Ozick also says that the biographers of Wharton and
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_11" n="N002"/>Woolf "missed the writer" in their subjects, and this is probably
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_12" n="N003"/>easier to do with women than with men. There is, still, a sort of
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_13" n="N004"/>trained-dog fascination with the idea of women writers—not that
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_14" n="N005"/>the thing is done well, but that it is done at all, by a creature
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_15" n="N006"/>that is not supposed to possess such capabilities. And so a biog-
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_16" n="N007"/>rapher may well focus on the woman, on gossip and sexual detail
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_17" n="N008"/>and domestic arrangements and political involvement, to the ex-
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_18" n="N009"/>clusion of the artist. But it is impossible to read any of the in-
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_19" n="N010"/>terviews in this book and "miss the writer." What these writers
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_20" n="N011"/>have in common is not their diverse responses to the category
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_21" n="N012"/>"woman writer," but their shared passion towards the category
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_22" n="N013"/>"writer."
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_23" n="N001"/>Reading through these interviews, I was struck again and again
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_24" n="N002"/>by the intensity of this passion: the commitment to craft, the
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_25" n="N003"/>informed admiration for the work of other writers from whom
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_26" n="N004"/>they have learned, the insistence on the importance, not of what
					<lb facs="#facs_7_l_27" n="N005"/>they themselves have done, but on what has been and can be
				</p>
				<pb n="8"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_1" n="N001"/>done through the art itself. In no other art, except painting,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_2" n="N002"/>perhaps, is the relationship of creation to creator so complex and
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_3" n="N003"/>personal and thus so potentially damaging to self-esteem: if you
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_4" n="N004"/>fail, you fail alone. The dancer realize someone else's dance,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_5" n="N005"/>the writer her own. The relationship of any writer towards a
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_6" n="N006"/>vocation so exacting in its specificity, so demanding of love and
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_7" n="N007"/>energy and time, so resistant to all efforts to define its essence or
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_8" n="N008"/>to categorize its best effects, is bound to be an edgy one, and in
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_9" n="N009"/>these conversations the edginess shows through. Some disclaim
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_10" n="N010"/>ego, remarkable in a collection of such strong, assertive, individ-
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_11" n="N011"/>ual voices; others keep secrets; others fence with their considerable
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_12" n="N012"/>intelligence; others protect themselves with wit. Some recom-
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_13" n="N013"/>mend objectivity, McCarthy's "sense"; others, like Edna O'Brien,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_14" n="N014"/>speak of necessary demons. It would be a brave person who would
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_15" n="N015"/>try to stuff these wonderful and various talents into one tidy box
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_16" n="N016"/>labelled “WW,” and expect that acronym to be definitive. Despite
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_17" n="N017"/>the title of this book, the lab I should probably read, “WWAAW,"
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_18" n="N018"/>Writers Who Are Also Women.
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_19" n="N001"/>This is not the only collection of such writers that could be
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_20" n="N002"/>made. It is limited in scope by the writers actually interviewed
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_21" n="N003"/>to date by The Paris Review. Thus, although there are writers
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_22" n="N004"/>from the United States, Ireland, England, Denmark, and South
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_23" n="N005"/>Africa, there are none here from, for instance, India or Australia
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_24" n="N006"/>or Canada or Latin America: no Alice Munro, no Anita Desai,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_25" n="N007"/>no Isabel Allende. As this assemblage is unisexual, so is it uni-
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_26" n="N008"/>colored: thus far no Toni Morrison, no Alice Walker, no Louise
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_27" n="N009"/>Erdrich. Nor are there many writers who are known for an explicit
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_28" n="N010"/>and self-aware examination of the more colonial features of the
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_29" n="N011"/>relationships between men as a group and women: no Marilyn
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_30" n="N012"/>French, no Marge Piercey, no Fay Weldon, no Adrienne Rich,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_31" n="N013"/>no Judith Rossner. Some of these omissions may be set down to
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_32" n="N014"/>the slowness characteristic of the mills of the gods and the editor
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_33" n="N015"/>of small magazines, a slowness which may account, too, for the
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_34" n="N016"/>retrospective slant of this volume. But looking back over the
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_35" n="N017"/>territory to see what has been done and, especially, said before,
					<lb facs="#facs_8_l_36" n="N018"/>is, in the case of writing, part of the territory.
				</p>
				<pb n="9"/>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_1" n="N001"/>To write is a solitary and singular act; to do it superbly, as all
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_2" n="N002"/>of these writers have done, is a blessing. Despite everything that
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_3" n="N003"/>gets said about the suffering and panic and horror of being a
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_4" n="N004"/>writer, the final impression left by these remarkable voices is one
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_5" n="N005"/>of thankfulness, of humility in the face of what has been given.
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_6" n="N006"/>From Joyce Carol Oates, one of the youngest writers in this group:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_10" n="N001"/>I take seriously Flaubert's statement must love
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_11" n="N002"/>one another in our art as the mystics love another in
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_12" n="N003"/>God. By honoring one another's creation we honor some-
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_13" n="N004"/>thing that deeply connected us all, and beyond us
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_14" n="N005"/>(Pp. 383-384)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l" n="N001"/>And from Dorothy Parker, one of the oldest:
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_8" n="N001"/>I want so much to write well, though I know I don't . . .
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_9" n="N002"/>But during and at the end of my life, I will adore those who
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_18" n="N003"/>have. (P. 119)
				</p>
				<p>
					<lb facs="#facs_9_l_19" n="N001"/>MARGARET ATWOOD, 1988
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
	<standOff type="annotation">
		
<xenoData>
			
<rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
				
<rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/" rdf:about="http://temp.lincsproject.ca/5YwP0OGEDJ1">
<![CDATA[{
    "@context": [
        "http://www.w3.org/ns/anno.jsonld",
        "https://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/json-ld_context.jsonld",
        "https://wa.lincsproject.ca/v1/ns/anno.jsonld"
    ],
    "id": "http://temp.lincsproject.ca/5YwP0OGEDJ1",
    "type": [
        "Annotation",
        "crm:E33_Linguistic_Object"
    ],
    "motivation": "oa:identifying",
    "created": "2026-05-19T20:32:11.092Z",
    "creator": {
        "id": "https://github.com/djakacki",
        "type": "crm:E21_Person",
        "name": "Diane Jakacki"
    },
    "generator": {
        "id": "https://nerve.lincsproject.ca",
        "type": [
            "Software",
            "crm:E73_Information_Object"
        ],
        "P16_used_specific_object": "https://nerve.lincsproject.ca",
        "name": "NERVE",
        "softwareVersion": "0.2.1"
    },
    "target": {
        "id": "/target/62Xu5uD8b4y",
        "type": [
            "SpecificResource",
            "crm:E73_Information_Object"
        ],
        "source": {
            "id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/guelphdh2026/main/WWaW_Atwood-Intro.xml",
            "type": "crm:D1_Digital_Object",
            "format": "application/tei+xml",
            "language": "en",
            "P1_is_identified_by": {
                "id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/guelphdh2026/main/WWaW_Atwood-Intro.xml/title",
                "type": "crm:E33_E41_Linguistic_Appellation",
                "title": "WWaW_Atwood-Intro"
            }
        },
        "selector": [
            {
                "id": "/target/62Xu5uD8b4y/selector/textPosition/7SUC6zfTgxb",
                "type": [
                    "TextPositionSelector",
                    "crm:E73_Information_Object"
                ],
                "start": 411,
                "end": 425,
                "refinedBy": {
                    "id": "/target/62Xu5uD8b4y/selector/textQuote/DxtXdRSUT78",
                    "type": [
                        "TextQuoteSelector",
                        "crm:E33_Linguistic_Object"
                    ],
                    "exact": "Marianne Moore",
                    "prefix": " That the editors have chosen to bring together,\n\t\t\t\t\twithin the same covers, fifteen writers as diverse as Dorothy Parker\n\t\t\t\t\tand Nadine Gordimer,",
                    "suffix": "and Rebecca West, Isak\n\t\t\t\t\tDinesen and Lillian Hellman, Mary McCarthy and Katherine\n\t\t\t\t\tAnne Porter, over what, in some cases, would doubtless be their\n\t\t\t\t\tdead bodies, merely because they share a double-X chronosome,\n\t\t\t\t\tis not due to a sudden mental aberration"
                }
            },
            {
                "id": "/target/62Xu5uD8b4y/selector/css/gyfkn9kuNHq",
                "type": [
                    "CssSelector",
                    "crm:E73_Information_Object"
                ],
                "value": "[ana~=webannotation:http://temp.lincsproject.ca/5YwP0OGEDJ1]"
            }
        ]
    },
    "body": {
        "id": "http://viaf.org/viaf/61562401",
        "type": "crm:E21_Person",
        "label": "Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.",
        "description": "Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972, poétesse"
    },
    "P2_has_type": [
        "oa:identifying"
    ]
}]]>
				
</rdf:Description>
				
<rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/" rdf:about="http://temp.lincsproject.ca/80kfuzKFLrX">
<![CDATA[{
    "@context": [
        "http://www.w3.org/ns/anno.jsonld",
        "https://www.cidoc-crm.org/cidoc-crm/json-ld_context.jsonld",
        "https://wa.lincsproject.ca/v1/ns/anno.jsonld"
    ],
    "id": "http://temp.lincsproject.ca/80kfuzKFLrX",
    "type": [
        "Annotation",
        "crm:E33_Linguistic_Object"
    ],
    "motivation": "oa:identifying",
    "created": "2026-05-19T20:33:57.799Z",
    "creator": {
        "id": "https://github.com/djakacki",
        "type": "crm:E21_Person",
        "name": "Diane Jakacki"
    },
    "generator": {
        "id": "https://nerve.lincsproject.ca",
        "type": [
            "Software",
            "crm:E73_Information_Object"
        ],
        "P16_used_specific_object": "https://nerve.lincsproject.ca",
        "name": "NERVE",
        "softwareVersion": "0.2.1"
    },
    "target": {
        "id": "/target/teMch06kCnx",
        "type": [
            "SpecificResource",
            "crm:E73_Information_Object"
        ],
        "source": {
            "id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/guelphdh2026/main/WWaW_Atwood-Intro.xml",
            "type": "crm:D1_Digital_Object",
            "format": "application/tei+xml",
            "language": "en",
            "P1_is_identified_by": {
                "id": "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/djakacki/guelphdh2026/main/WWaW_Atwood-Intro.xml/title",
                "type": "crm:E33_E41_Linguistic_Appellation",
                "title": "WWaW_Atwood-Intro"
            }
        },
        "selector": [
            {
                "id": "/target/teMch06kCnx/selector/textPosition/mA1t33Q0k6u",
                "type": [
                    "TextPositionSelector",
                    "crm:E73_Information_Object"
                ],
                "start": 1635,
                "end": 1641,
                "refinedBy": {
                    "id": "/target/teMch06kCnx/selector/textQuote/Vmw4sOPmiqR",
                    "type": [
                        "TextQuoteSelector",
                        "crm:E33_Linguistic_Object"
                    ],
                    "exact": "Milton",
                    "prefix": " Paradise Lost reads dif-\n\t\t\t\t\n\t\t\t\t\n\t\t\t\t\n\t\t\t\t\tferently when viewed by the daughters of Eve, and with",
                    "suffix": "s\n\t\t\t\t\tbrowbeaten secretarial daughters in mind; and so on down\n\t\t\t\t\tthrough the canon"
                }
            },
            {
                "id": "/target/teMch06kCnx/selector/css/nBWzVQYarnM",
                "type": [
                    "CssSelector",
                    "crm:E73_Information_Object"
                ],
                "value": "[ana~=webannotation:http://temp.lincsproject.ca/80kfuzKFLrX]"
            }
        ]
    },
    "body": {
        "id": "http://viaf.org/viaf/17226855",
        "type": "crm:E21_Person",
        "label": "Milton, John, 1608-1674.",
        "description": "Milton, John, poète, 1608-1674"
    },
    "P2_has_type": [
        "oa:identifying"
    ]
}]]>
				
</rdf:Description>
			
</rdf:RDF>
		
</xenoData>
	</standOff>
</TEI>